<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cryspen on Dr Franziskus Kiefer</title>
    <link>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/tags/cryspen/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cryspen on Dr Franziskus Kiefer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/tags/cryspen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is High Assurance Cryptography?</title>
      <link>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/p/what-is-high-assurance-cryptography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/p/what-is-high-assurance-cryptography/</guid>
      <description>With my company Cryspen we build high assurance cryptography. But what does this actually mean?
Before focusing on cryptography it is interesting to look at high assurance software in general. How is high assurance software different from other software?
High assurance software is usually seen as being more trustworthy than other software. This is especially interesting in high-risk/high-stakes environments such as financial institutions or governments. There are different ways to achieve better guarantees for software.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Executable HPKE Specification</title>
      <link>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/p/an-executable-hpke-specification/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/p/an-executable-hpke-specification/</guid>
      <description>HPKE, published as RFC 9180, describes a scheme for hybrid public key encryption.
 📚 Please go and read our TL;DR on HPKE if you nee more background on HPKE.
 In this I describe the first executable HPKE specification using hacspec. It is not only an executable specification of HPKE, it is also an annotated version of the RFC that can be read instead of (or in addition to) the RFC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TL;DR - Hybrid Public Key Encryption</title>
      <link>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/p/tldr-hybrid-public-key-encryption/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/p/tldr-hybrid-public-key-encryption/</guid>
      <description>HPKE is a CFRG in RFC 9180 that describes a scheme for hybrid public key encryption. It is co-authored by my Cryspen co-founder Karthikeyan Bhargavan and one of his PhD students Benjamin Lipp as part of his research at Inria.
This blog post will give a brief overview of the specification and describes some use cases.
If you want to learn more about the security proofs behind HPKE and the RFC process, Benjamin wrote an excellent blog post about it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cryspen ERC PoC Grant</title>
      <link>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/p/cryspen-erc-poc-grant/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.franziskuskiefer.de/p/cryspen-erc-poc-grant/</guid>
      <description>My co-founder Karthik got awarded an ERC Proof of Concept grant for commercialising the know-how and landmark research results from his Inria research group PROSECCO through Cryspen.
Announcement Cryptographic mechanisms are crucial to the security of our digital lives but their design and implementation remains notoriously difficult and error-prone. With the help of two ERC Grants, Karthikeyan Bhargavan and the Prosecco team at Inria have developed state-of-the-art formal verification techniques that can be applied to real-world cryptographic software.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
